"A Testimonial from Dr. Ornish's
Alzheimer's Progression Reversal Study"
On Friday,
I released a video
profiling Dr. Dean Ornish’s
landmark new study
in the leading peer-reviewed
Alzheimer’s translational
research journal,
a randomized controlled trial
showing that a plant-based
diet and lifestyle program
may significantly improve
cognition and function
after 20 weeks in many patients
with early-stage Alzheimer's disease.
About 70% remained stable
or actually improved
in the plant-based
intervention group,
whereas,
in the control group,
about 70% got worse and
not a single person got better.
But no matter how
significant the results,
the dry statistics just don’t
convey the human impact.
Many patients who
experienced improvement
reported regaining cognition
and function they had lost,
but how does that actually
translate into real life?
Well, for example, several
patients in the intervention group
reported that they had been unable
to read a book or watch a movie
because they kept forgetting what
they just read or watched
and had to keep starting over,
but after the plant-based diet
and lifestyle changes,
they got better,
such that now they were able
to read and watch shows again.
One individual reported that
it used to take him weeks
to ﬁnish reading a book,
but after participating in the study,
he was able to do it
in a matter of days.
Another participant,
a former business executive,
reported regaining the ability to manage
his own ﬁnances and investments.
“It was so much
a part of my life”, he said,
“who I am, and who I was—
it was hard saying that
part of me was just gone.
But now I’m back to
reconciling our ﬁnances monthly;
I keep up to date
on our investments.
A lot of self-worth
comes back.”
Another one said that for ﬁve
years she had been unable
to prepare their family
business’s ﬁnancial reports,
but now she is able
to do so accurately.
“A deep sense of
identity is returning.
It’s given me a
new lease on life,
and yet it’s a familiarity and something
I’ve always prided myself on.
I’m coming back like I was prior to the
Alzheimer’s disease being diagnosed.
I feel like I’m me again—
an older but better version of me.”
But even words are hard to
describe such transformations.
One of Dr. Ornish’s study participants
gave us permission to share his story.
Dan Jones, a musician at
military events and parades,
who was diagnosed
with Alzheimer's disease.
"What do you notice that you could
do now that you couldn't do before?"
"Well, for one thing,
I had a set of about eight tunes
that I played in the parade.
And I could just go straight through
them from one into the other.
I played for an hour and
a half without stopping.
I think it was pretty close.
They move darn
slow in that parade.
I was leaving them
behind walking.
I kept having to stop and
wait for them to catch up."
"Was that something different?"
"Yeah."
"And what was?"
"Well, that I could
remember the order.
I could make the transition from
tune to tune without messing up
and getting confused about
which tune I was playing.
Those were all problems I'd
had when we were playing
at the graduation ceremony.
You know,
I'd forget which tune
was coming next.
I'd get worried about it,
and I'd start making mistakes.
And this just went
like clockwork.
A lot of it had to do with practice,
but the tunes we played before,
I had played hundreds of times.
And I was messing up,
and in the parade,
I hardly messed up at all."
"And you were messing up because
you had a hard time remembering?"
"Because I had a hard
time remembering.
I'd get confused
about different tunes.
It was really, yeah, it was
not a pleasant experience.
It was unpleasant enough that,
like I said,
I went home and put them down.
And now, there was one
day a couple of weeks ago
when I really had
the drones in tune.
It was in the evening,
I was out on the
front porch playing,
and it was just so beautiful.
I played for 2 hours.
I just stood there and played."
"What are you feeling now?"
"Joy. Just happy.
You know, women always say they're
crying because they're happy.
I'm crying because I'm happy.
It was just so nice to
be able to do that again."
"Did that make you feel
better about yourself too?"
"It did."
"In what way?"
"I just felt like I
could do something.
I had worth again,
so to speak.
Something that was important
to me was given back."
Here’s what the head
of Harvard’s Brain Center
at Mass General had to say:
Big Pharma has invested
billions in the effort
to ﬁnd medications
to treat the disease,
but only two Alzheimer’s drugs have
been approved in the last 20 years—
one of which was already
just pulled off the market,
and the other is minimally effective,
extremely expensive,
and often has
pesky side effects
such as brain swelling
or bleeding into the brain.
In contrast, the intensive lifestyle
changes implemented in this study
have been shown here to
improve cognition and function,
at the cost of, like,
buying broccoli,
and the only side
effects are positive ones.